Guide to the Connecticut Training School for Nurses Records and Memorabilia
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Connecticut Training School for Nurses records and memorabilia
1786-1954
RU 231
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
35.25
The records consist of policy and financial records, reports, correspondence, student records and notebooks, photographs, and alumnae records documenting the operations of the Connecticut Training School for Nurses. Topics include curriculum, administration, organization, social work, legal issues, funding, personnel, and social events. Included are two historical sketches of the school by Francis Bacon, a key personality in its founding, and Henry W. Farnum, its president.
Connecticut Training School for Nurses
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 37 (YRG 37), Records of associations, institutes, centers, and organizations affiliated with Yale University.
Biographical / Historical
The Connecticut Training School for Nurses was established in 1873 as an independent school charged with training nurses to provide service to the community. The school quickly developed a relationship with the New Haven Hospital. With financial assistance from the Rockefeller Foundation, the Yale School of Nursing superseded the Connecticut Training School for Nurses in 1926. The Connecticut Training School for Nurses is credited with publishing the first nursing textbook in 1879.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of policy and financial records, reports, correspondence, student records and notebooks, photographs, and alumnae records documenting the operations of the Connecticut Training School for Nurses. Topics include curriculum, administration, organization, social work, legal issues, funding, personnel, and social events. Included are two historical sketches of the school by Francis Bacon, a key personality in its founding, and Henry W. Farnum, its president.
Arrangement
The records are arranged as follows: I. Policy Records and Reports, 1873-1943. II. Correspondence, 1808-1920. III. Financial Records, 1898-1928. IV. Student Notebooks, Exams, Course Outlines, 1892-1923. V. Student Records, 1875-1926. VI. Diplomas and Certificates, 1883-1918. VII. Alumnae Records, 1873-1935. VIII. Photographs, 1875-1948. IX. Memorabilia, 1846-1894. X. Printed Matter, 1786-1926. XI. Newspaper Clippings, 1919-1931; and subsequent accessions.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Hospitals -- Employees; Hospitals -- Connecticut; Nursing schools; Nursing -- Study and teaching; Nurses; Bacon, Francis, 1831-1912; Farnam, Henry W. (Henry Walcott), 1853-1933; Connecticut Training School for Nurses; New Haven Hospital (New Haven, Conn.); Yale University -- Students; Yale University. School of Nursing
- Policy Records and Reports, Series I
  - Annual Reports
    - 1st to 53rd (individual), 1875-1926 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
    - 1st to 44th (bound in groups), 1874-1917 (Box 2, Folder 6-8)
    - 1st to 26th (hard cover book), 1874-1900 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 27th to 49th (hard cover book), 1901-1922 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Charter, Constitution and By-laws
    - Charter: the Connecticut Training School, copy, 1873 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Charter: General Hospital Society of Connecticut, by-laws and regulations, 1892-1924 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Constitution and by-laws amended, 1883 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Constitution and by-laws adopted, 1913 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Agreements
    - Hospital directors with officers of the Training School: amendment, 1873-1919 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Hospital Society, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Nurses, 1911-1919 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Nurses, Head, 1884-1909 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Prudential Committee and Executive Committee: allocation of nurses, 1888 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Executive Committee Minutes and Correspondence
    - Medical Boards: minutes and correspondence, 1883-1884 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous minutes of meetings, lists and notes: Executive Committee, 1916-1924 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Monthly and annual meetings of Executive Committee: minutes, 1906-1916 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Monthly and annual meeting of Executive Committee: minutes, 1919-1924 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Monthly reports of the director, 1919-1927 (Box 4, Folder 24-32)
    - Prospectus: School of Nursing, 1916-1919 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Historical Sketch: Henry W. Farnam, president, other papers on history of school, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - History: material from bound volume "Records of The Connecticut Training School for Nurses", 1873-1926 (Box 4, Folder 35-39)
    - Foundation of Connecticut Training School for Nurses: Francis Bacon, 1895 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Miscellaneous Records
    - Allocation of nurses, 1892-1908 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Bulletin of Yale University, 1943-1949 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Class songs, 1910-1919 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Commencement: programs of exercises, 1912-1926 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Gillian, Charles A., Surgeon: dismissal, 1884 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Hospital regulations, undated (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Inspection reports of areas in hospital by hospital heads (Board of Visitors), 1917 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Invitations: graduations, centennial celebrations, services, 1910-1926 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Lists, memoranda, pamphlets, 1898-1926 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - Missionary nurses among the poor, 1887-1888 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - New Haven Hospital- Connecticut Training School: report, 1873 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Nurses' notices and announcements: originals and copies, 1919-1923 (Box 6, Folder 52-59)
    - Pamphlets, 1891-1934 (Box 6, Folder 60)
    - Questionnaires: memoranda, 1916-1923 (Box 6, Folder 61)
    - Semi-Centennial Celebration: tickets issued, notebooks, lists, 1923 (Box 6, Folder 62)
    - School of Medicine: Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology monthly seminar: record of meetings, 1939-1940 (Box 6, Folder 63)
    - Social activities in the Recreational Unit: correspondence, memoranda, pamphlets, 1931-1933 (Box 6, Folder 64)
    - State Hospital and Connecticut Training School for Nurses, 1873 (Box 6, Folder 65)
    - The Laying-in Asylum and Infirmary, New York: record of nurses who trainied here for period of time, 1887 (Box 6, Folder 66)
- Correspondence, Series II
  - General
    - 1808-1920, 1881-1910, 1912-1933 (Box 7, Folder 1-5)
  - Building of nurses' home (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - General Hospital of New Haven, 1879-1909 (Box 7, Folder 7-9)
  - Legal, 1905-1926 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Other training schools, 1905 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Financial Records, Series III
  - Bank deposit books, 1901-1903 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Budget: ledgers, 1898-1913 (Box 8, Folder 2-5)
  - Cancelled checks, 1943-1947 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Check books, 1905-1911 (Box 9, Folder 7-9)
  - Expense accounts for services of nurses, 1899-1908 (Box 9, Folder 10-11)
  - Expense accounts for services of nurses, 1909-1914 (Box 10, Folder 12-13)
  - Funds of the Alumnae Association: the Union and New Haven Trust Company, 1928-1944 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Receipted bills: home and uniform accounts, salaries and some payroll, 1898-1901 (Box 10, Folder 15-17)
  - Receipted bills: home and uniform accounts, salaries and some payroll, 1902-1905 (Box 11, Folder 18-21)
  - Receipted bills: home and uniform accounts, salaries and some payroll, 1906-1927 (Box 12, Folder 22-29)
  - Receipts for services of nurses, 1905-1908 (Box 13, Folder 29-34)
  - Receipts for services of nurses, 1909-1910 (Box 14, Folder 35-40)
  - Receipts for services of nurses, 1911-1912 (Box 15, Folder 41-44)
  - Time and payroll books, 1898-1911 (Box 16, Folder 45-49)
  - Time and payroll books, 1911-1921 (Box 17, Folder 50-54)
  - Time and payroll books, 1921-1927 (Box 18, Folder 55-57)
- Student Notebooks, Exams, Course Outlines, Series IV
  - Notebook: food recipes, formulas, notes, 1892 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Outlines and examinations, 1918-1923 (Box 19, Folder 2-6)
- Student Records, Series V
  - Subject File
    - Assignment of Nurses, 1902-1913 (Box 20, Folder 1-6)
    - Census: list of nurses activities by supervisors, 1906-1910 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Class work reports, 1918-1926 (Box 20, Folder 8-9)
    - Examination of student nurses, Report on, 1923 (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Graduate student information, 1882-1889 (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - Graduate student information, 1875-1889 (Box 21, Folder 12)
      General
      See also: box 52, folder 4
    - Miscellaneous, 1914-1926 (Box 22, Folder 13)
    - Nurses records, 1913-1916 (Box 22, Folder 14)
    - The second year of graduates from the school, record of, 1875-1877 (Box 22, Folder 15)
  - Students Accepted: By Year of Graduation
    - 1902 A-W (Box 23, Folder 17-31)
    - 1903 A-W (Box 23, Folder 32-43)
    - 1904 A-W (Box 23, Folder 44-58)
    - 1905 A-S (Box 23, Folder 59-75)
    - 1905 Sm-W (Box 24, Folder 76-79)
    - 1906 A-W (Box 24, Folder 80-93)
    - 1907 A-W (Box 24, Folder 94-115)
    - 1908 A-W (Box 25, Folder 116-139)
    - 1909 A-W (Box 26, Folder 140-159)
    - 1910 A-M (Box 26, Folder 160-171)
    - 1910 M-W (Box 27, Folder 172-181)
    - 1911 A-J (Box 27, Folder 182-198)
    - 1911 K-W (Box 28, Folder 199-211)
    - 1912 A-W (Box 28, Folder 212-228)
    - 1913 A-Y (Box 29, Folder 229-258)
    - 1914 A-H (Box 29, Folder 259-272)
    - 1914 K-W (Box 30, Folder 273-291)
    - 1915 A-R (Box 30, Folder 292-313)
    - 1915 Ro-W (Box 31, Folder 314-321)
    - 1916 A-W (Box 31, Folder 322-349)
    - 1917 A-W (Box 32, Folder 350-382)
    - 1918 A-W (Box 33, Folder 383-403)
    - 1918 A-W (Box 34, Folder 404-428)
    - 1920 A-W (Box 35, Folder 429-451)
    - 1921 A-S (Box 36, Folder 452-468)
    - 1921 St-V (Box 37, Folder 469-472)
    - 1922 A-K (Box 37, Folder 473-486)
    - 1922 M-V (Box 38, Folder 487-496)
    - 1923 A-H (Box 38, Folder 497-504)
    - 1923 K-W (Box 39, Folder 505-515)
    - 1924 A-B (Box 39, Folder 516-519)
    - 1924 C-W (Box 40, Folder 520-537)
    - 1925 A-Z (Box 41, Folder 538-550)
    - 1926 A-C (Box 41, Folder 551-556)
    - 1926 C-Y (Box 42, Folder 557-568)
  - Affiliates and Post-Graduates: Alphabetical
    - 1920-1925 A-H (Box 42, Folder 569-596)
    - 1919-1926 J-W (Box 43, Folder 597-648)
  - Withdrawals: By Year of Intended Graduation
    - 1902 H (Box 44, Folder 649)
    - 1903 G (Box 44, Folder 650)
    - 1908 G (Box 44, Folder 651)
    - 1912 B-V (Box 44, Folder 652-662)
    - 1913 B-W (Box 44, Folder 663-665)
    - 1914 B-O (Box 44, Folder 666-683)
    - 1914 P-S (Box 45, Folder 684-688)
    - 1915 G (Box 45, Folder 689)
    - 1916 B-W (Box 45, Folder 690-705)
    - 1917 B-R (Box 45, Folder 706-715)
    - 1918 A-Y (Box 46, Folder 716-734)
    - 1919 A-W (Box 46, Folder 735-755)
    - 1920 A-W (Box 47, Folder 756-783)
    - 1921 B (Box 47, Folder 784-792)
    - 1921 C-T (Box 48, Folder 793-812)
    - 1922 C-H (Box 48, Folder 813-819)
    - 1922 M-W (Box 49, Folder 820-826)
    - 1923 B-W (Box 49, Folder 827-837)
    - 1924 C-M (Box 50, Folder 838-844)
    - 1925 A-V (Box 50, Folder 845-854)
    - 1926 B-K (Box 50, Folder 855-861)
    - 1926 L-W (Box 51, Folder 862-871)
- Diplomas and Certificates, Series VI
  - Blank diplomas (Box 52, Folder 1)
  - War Savings Certificates, 1918-1919 (Box 52, Folder 2)
  - Emma Stowe, Superintendent of Nurses: awards from governor, 1907 (Box 52, Folder 3)
  - Student diplomas, certificates and awards, 1883-1905 (Box 52, Folder 4)
- Alumnae Records, Series VII
  - Addresses: activities: obituary notices, 1873-1920 (Box 53, Folder 1-7)
  - Addresses: activities: obituary notices, 1921-1926 (Box 54, Folder 8)
  - Obituary Record, 1876-1926 (Box 54, Folder 9)
  - Membership lists, pamphlets, 1875-1935 (Box 54, Folder 10)
- Photographs, Series VIII
  - Alumni dinner, undated (Box 55, Folder 1)
  - Anniversaries: Connecticut Training School 75th/Yale School of Nursing 25th, 1948 (Box 55, Folder 1)
  - Effie Taylor and Annie Goodrich, undated (Box 55, Folder 2)
  - Individuals and groups, 1875-1940, undated (Box 55, Folder 3-10)
  - Old New Haven Hospital, 1897, undated (Box 55, Folder 11-12)
  - Metal cuts of pictures used for publicity and recruitment of nurses during World War I, undated (Box 56, Folder 13-16)
  - Metal cuts of pictures used for publicity and recruitment of nurses during World War I, undated (Box 57, Folder 17-21)
  - Groups (oversize), 1891-1921, undated (Box 58)
- Memorabilia, Series IX
  - Class pins, 1887-1894 (Box 59, Folder 1)
  - Commemoration of one hundredth anniversary of the first public demonstration of surgical anaesthesia at the Massachusetts General Hospital, 1946 (Box 59, Folder 2)
  - Prints depicting the use of surgical anaesthesia, 1889, 1896 (Box 59, Folder 3)
  - Leather case with set of instruments, undated (Box 59, Folder 4)
  - Missionary Nurse Cross: New Haven Hospital, undated (Box 59, Folder 5)
  - Finger rings carved from bones of beef rations by convalescents in the Portsmouth General Military Hospital, 1863 (Box 59, Folder 6)
  - First uniforms worn by nurses
    - Blue checked uniform: skirt and bodice, aprons, belt, long cuffs and some pieces of material (Box 60)
    - Blue and white all-in-one uniform: apron with attached long cuffs (Box 60)
    - Caps: pattern of first cap, first cap and several later ones (Box 60)
    - 2 aprons and short cuffs (Box 60)
    - 1 small (child's) uniform: blue and white checked and striped (Box 60)
    - 1 blue and white checked apron (child's) (Box 60)
    - 1 white apron, 1 white bib (child's) (Box 60)
- Printed Matter: Nursing Publications and Other Textbooks, Series X
  - Nursing Textbooks
    - A Classic Book for Nurses: Hoggson and Robinson, 1877 (Box 61, Folder 1)
    - A New Way of Training Nurses: A. Worcester, A.M., M.D., 1888 (Box 61, Folder 1)
    - Class Book: Connecticut Training School (Box 61, Folder 2)
    - Class Book: Yale School of Nursing, 1926 (Box 61, Folder 2)
    - Church Hymns and Gospel Songs (Box 61, Folder 3)
    - Sankey, McGranahan, Stebbins (2 copies), 1898 (Box 61, Folder 3)
    - Community Songs (a collection: notebook), 1919 (Box 61, Folder 3)
    - Handbook of Nursing: published under direction of Connecticut Training School, 1884 (Box 61, Folder 4)
    - Handbook of Nursing: published under direction of Connecticut Training School, 1905 (Box 61, Folder 5)
    - Hospital Notes for Probationers, 1904 (Box 61, Folder 6)
    - Hospital Notes, 1892 (Box 61, Folder 6)
    - Nursing News, 1962 (Box 61, Folder 6)
    - Woods-Medical Lexicon: St. John Rose, 1890 (Box 61, Folder 6)
  - Non-Nursing Textbooks
    - History of the United States of America: Henry Watson - J. Harris Patton, 1881 (Box 62, Folder 7)
    - The Complete Poetical Works: Burns and Scott, 1786 (Box 63, Folder 8)
    - Caskell's Popular Atlas of the World, 1890 (Box 64, Folder 8)
- Newspaper Clippings, Series XI
  - Want ads for nurses needed: Advertisements of Schools of Nursing, 1919-1921 (Box 65, Folder 1-2)
  - Miscellaneous articles concerning nursing, 1921-1931 (Box 65, Folder 3-5)
- Records and textbooks, 1877-1949; Accession 1985-A-003
  - Class Book for Nurses, 1877 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Text book prepared for Connecticut Training School, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and papers regarding the Connecticut Training School being in the Will of Clara A. Blakeslee, 1939-1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Alumnae list, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Nursing notebook of Clara Evelyn Atkins, 1917; Accession 1995-A-032
  - Nursing notebook of Clara Evelyn Atkins, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Student records and meeting minutes, 1883-1954; Accession 2007-A-159
  Scope and Contents
  The records consist of bound student record ledgers and minutes of monthly and annual meetings of the Connecticut Training School of Nurses.
  - Meeting minutes, 1924-1954 (Box 1)
  - Student records
    - circa 1880-1890 (Box 1)
    - 1891- circa 1900 (Box 1)
    - 1898-1904 (Box 2)
    - 1904-1912 (Box 2)
    - 1908-1913 (Box 2)
- Connecticut Training School for Nurses procedures manuals and class book, circa 1877, 1954; Accession 2009-A-001
  - Connecticut Training School for Nurses
    - Manual, 1877 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Class book, 1877 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Grace-New Haven Community Hospital
    - Manual of nursing procedures, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)